welcome to another edition of the UK
lore weekly podcast with me your host
Marcus cleaver this week we're looking
in the case of Prudential Assurance
Company Limited and HMRC and the
citation for this case is 2018 UK SC 39
and it's quite a complex tax law case
that we're looking at today so we're
gonna examine the facts as usual but
then probably just focus on the main
conclusion reached by the Supreme Court
the company is a test claimant and so
the real focus is going to be on trying
to examine the state of the law between
1990 and 2009 and its heart there is a
disparity between how investments in
uk-based companies are treated for tax
purposes
compared to investments in overseas
companies and in the previous case the
Court of Justice of the European Union
and ruled that this disparity was not
allowed to find out what the
consequences of that decision worth of
the companies that had paid too much tax
and the case was needed and that is what
we have before the Supreme Court today
before we get into that decision however
it is worth briefly going over how the
law previously operated under the income
and corporation taxes Act 1988 otherwise
known as Ector when you invest in a
company you can receive something called
dividends which is money that represents
a return on your investment as the
company grows section 208 established
that when both the company handing out
the dividend and the company receiving
the dividend were based in the UK there
not only was the recipient exempt from
corporation taxed but they would also
receive tax credit that was equal to the
amount of corporation tax that the
distributing company had paid in advance
also known as advanced corporation tax
altogether the dividends plus the tax
credit represented something called
franked investment income and could be
used to reduce a company's own liability
to pay advance corporation tax when it
came to paying dividends out to its own
investors on the other hand Asda
invested in overseas companies received
no such benefit and so they had to pay
called
raishin tax and were not entitled to tax
credit we've already noted that this
disparity was illegal under EU law but
it was unclear how much tax and tax
credit should be repaid by HMRC and so
that's where the Supreme Court comes in
to explain the main thrust of the ruling
it is useful to give a brief overview of
the difference between simple and
compound interest and to do that we will
need to imagine that you have for
example 50 pounds in a bank account if
we got 10% simple interest per year then
each year we would get 5 pounds so at
the end of the first year we would have
55 pounds after 2 years we would have 60
pounds and after 3 years 65 pounds etc
however compound interest is where we
basically get interest on our interest
so 10% interest compounded annually
would still give us 55 pounds after one
year but in the second year we would get
10% of that which is 5 pounds 50 so we
would end up with 60 pounds 50 in the
second year in the third year then we
would end up with 66 pounds 55 pence and
it goes up like that basically you can
see from this that compound interest
pays more than simple interest so
Prudential who were getting money back
from HMRC dating back many years wanted
compound interest have been applied
where as HMRC argued in favor of simple
interest from a purely legal perspective
it was Prudential who had the better
argument going in as the recent case of
Sempra metals Limited and Inland Revenue
Commissioners from 2007 had established
that compound interest would be
available in cases of unjust enrichment
breaking down the definition of unjust
enrichment we can see the firstly Haiti
mercy have been enriched through the
extra money that has flowed into their
coffers that enrichment came at the
expense of Prudential who had to pay
more tax during the period in question
the enrichment was unjust as established
in the previous case before the court of
justice and finally there is no
applicable defense that can be used in
this particular scenario
so that should be case closed then well
in actual fact no because the justices
decided to unanimously overrule Sempra
metals and did say for a few good
reasons in the first instance another
recent case called little woods retail
limited and revenue and customs
commissioners from 2017 made it clear
that in order to meet the EU requirement
of an effective remedy simple interest
was sufficient that alone though is not
enough of a justification and so the
Supreme Court also looked at domestic
tax legislation such as section 78 of
the v80 Act 1994 and section 826 of
Ector that explicitly provides for
simple interest but were missing from
the final Sempra metals decision another
important factor is the section 320 of
the 2004 Finance Act gives HMRC a much
greater degree of flexibility when it
comes to the law of limitation and how
swiftly a claimant has to bring an
action cases from around that time such
as Klein wall Benson from 1999 really
highlighted how much of an issue
retrospective 'ti could be in related
cases even thinking about the overruling
in terms of policy factors there is a
real issue that these types of cases
could potentially cost the UK taxpayer
billions of pounds not simply by virtue
of the case itself but by that important
distinction between simple and compound
interest in the Littlewoods case that
difference was estimated at around 17
billion pounds and well that should not
be a decisive factor when establishing a
legal ruling is undeniably a significant
figure finally the decision in the case
also offered a chance to take another
look at the law on unjust enrichment we
mentioned earlier that the opportunity T
used the money there had been unfairly
claimed as tax revenue represented a
benefit to the government but the
Supreme Court pointed out that this
should not be regarded as something
extra beyond the simple receipt of the
money itself the best comparison is with
a debt where by the late payment of a
debt attracts interest as a form of
compensation for not being able to use
money but there is no further action for
unjust enrichment to whatever extent
there is an extra advantage it does not
come at the expense of the claimant in
such a case in the end HMRC was
successful on this crucial ground awhile
Prudential were successful on some of
the other grounds such as ensuring that
the refund would be calculated according
to the rate of tax rather than the
actual tax paid even this was something
of a Pyrrhic victory as in a number of
instances that mode of calculation will
actually work out better for the
government on balance I think that the
decision to overturn the decision in
Sempra was right that is not to say this
emperor was necessarily an abhorrent
decision that needed overturning it had
some logic to it and presented both a
clear advantage to parties that had lost
out on money and being punitive to those
including the government who had
mistakenly taken that money and gained a
benefit by doing so nevertheless the
legislation does clearly point to an
application of simple interest and the
analogy with a debt does clear up the
question on and just enrichment it
shouldn't be underestimated just how
much of a win this is for the government
who estimated that if they had to pay
compound interest would have ended up as
much as 5 billion pounds down that
figure also doesn't include the amount
will be saved when the decision in
Prudential is applied to other similar
cases and so the legal fees spent
pursuing this case were well justified
more broadly the original decision was
based on an illegal discrimination that
favored investment in UK companies
whether such legislation returns after
the UK leaves the European Union will be
an interesting bellwether to see what
direction the country is heading on the
one hand retaining a parity with other
countries and removing any
discrimination will show that Britain is
open for investment and that companies
will have to compete on their own merit
with no favor shown on the basis of
nationality on the other hand if the
government decides to try and protect UK
businesses in this way then it will
pretend a much darker future where
investment both
and out of the country slowly declines
and any ideas about competing on a
global stage will be out of reach
well thank you very much for tuning in
to another episode of the UK law weekly
podcast
and thanks as over to Ben sangkum who
provide the theme music special thanks
this week goes to dig how you Patel who
left a very kind review of the podcast
on iTunes and I can only apologize to
him for probably pronouncing his name
completely wrong also a news from me and
on the YouTube channel youtube.com
forward slash Marcus cleaver latest
video is on whistleblowing and in the
context of employment law so check that
if you do get a chance I'll be back with
another episode next week but for now
[Music]